<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="funct.css" type="text/css"?>
<?xm-well_formed path="funct.dtd"?>
<slides>
 <lang>en</lang>
  <title>Accessibility 101</title>
  <name>Jon Gunderson, Ph.D.</name>
  <desc href="http://disability.illinois.edu">Division of Disability Resources and Educational Services</desc>
  <desc href="http://ahs.illinois.edu">College of Applied Health Sciences</desc>
  <desc href="http://illinois.edu">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</desc>
  <email>jongund@illinois.edu</email>

  <stylesheet media="screen">../../common/css/bootstrap.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../../common/css/bootstrap-theme.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../../common/css/bootstrap-accessibility.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../../common/css/xml-slides.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../../common/css/highlight.css</stylesheet>
  <script>../../common/js/jquery-2.1.1.min.js</script>
  <script>../../common/js/bootstrap.min.js</script>
  <script>../../common/js/bootstrap-accessibility.min.js</script>
  <script>../../common/js/highlight.pack.js</script>
  <script>../../common/js/xml-slides.js</script>

  <slide>
    <title>Accessibility 101 Overview</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Accommodation versus Universal Design</li>
        <li>Accessibility Laws</li>
      </ul>
      <script type="text/javascript">
        slideShowURL()
      </script>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Most Important Things You Can Do!</title>
    <contents>
      <p>Ask vendors about accessibility:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Accessible <em>design</em> standards and practices.</li>
        <li>Employ people with disabilities.</li>
        <li>Testing practices and procedures.</li>
        <li>How their product supports you in creating and maintaining accessible content.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>What is Disability?</title>
    <contents>

      <p>Disability is not a single phenomenon, and does not have a single definition. Different individuals experience disability in different ways that are informed by myriad personal, social, and cultural factors.</p>

      <p>People often identify disability in functional terms, such as:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>Visual disabilities (e.g., blindness, low vision, color blindness)</li>
        <li>Auditory disabilities (e.g., deafness, hard of hearing)</li>
        <li>Motor disabilities (e.g., paralysis, cerebral palsy, missing/damaged limbs)</li>
        <li>Cognitive disabilities (e.g., autism, Down Syndrome, traumatic brain injury (TBI), attention deficit disorder (ADD), dyslexia (difficulty reading), learning disabilities in general)</li>
        <li>Psychological disabilities (e.g., depression, anxiety, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder.</li>
        <li>Seizure disabilities (e.g., epilepsy)</li>
        <li>Age-related loss of function (e.g., diminished sensory acuity, dexterity, stamina)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Even within a disability type, there is large diversity. For example, a person may identify as being blind, yet this does not always mean that they have 100% loss of vision. Again, unique, diverse, and not always visible.</p>

    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>W3C Perspective Videos</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/perspective-videos/" target="_video">All Perspectives</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/perspective-videos/keyboard/" target="_video">Keyboard</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/perspective-videos/voice/" target="_video">Voice Recognition</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/perspective-videos/captions/" target="_video">Captioning</a></li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title>Personal Experiences</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Blind law student: KP</li>
        <li>Relative with reading disability: AM</li>
        <li>Legally blind network administrator: MC</li>
        <li>Student software developer: MK</li>
        <li>What are some of your experiences?</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Medical and Social Models of Disability</title>
    <contents>
<p>Of many frameworks that attempt to provide perspective and clarity to disability issues, perhaps the two most prominent are the “medical” and “social” models of disability.</p>

<p style="text-align: center"><img src="images/medical-social-model.png" alt="Medical and social model"/></p>

<dl>
  <dt>Medical Model</dt>
  <dd>The medical model asserts that disability is primarily the result of an individual’s impairments. In this model, disability is seen as a shortcoming, linked to the individual that requires correction or accommodation. In order to participate in school, employment, and other social institutions, an individual must seek assistance.</dd>

  <dt>Social Model</dt>
  <dd>By contrast, the social model asserts that society creates barriers that disable people; that disability is the result of social systems and environments that fail to take into account the full range of human capability. In this model, it is the systems that must be reimagined and adapted so that they are accessible and useable to people across a spectrum of ability levels.</dd>
</dl>
    </contents>
  </slide>

<slide>
  <title>Accommodation vs. Accessibility</title>
  <contents>

    <p>It is important to note that not all disabilities are apparent, take for example cognitive disabilities like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and dyslexia, or psychological disabilities such as mental health conditions. People all-too-frequently doubt the existence of non-apparent disabilities or play-down their effects, and it is counterproductive to consider disabilities this way.</p>

    <p>Instead of categorizing disabilities into “visible” vs “invisible” or “apparent” vs “non-apparent”, it is more useful to consider barriers that might exist in any given context.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center"><img src="images/equality-equity-liberation.jpg" alt="Children of different heights watching a baseball game from the outfield illustrating the concept of equality, equity, liberation" title="detailed description follows"/></p>

    <p>This graphic shows three versions of the same scene. There are three people trying to watch a baseball game from behind the outfield fence. One is tall enough to see over the fence without a riser, the other two are not. We will talk more about each of these in the following pages, yet let's state some facts first.</p>

    <p>The first frame labeled "<em>equality</em>", everyone has the same restrictions:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>The three individuals are of different heights.</li>
      <li>Each individual has an identical box (we will call them "accommodations") to stand on.</li>
      <li>There is a fence (we will call this "the barrier") in front of the three,</li>
      <li>This arrangement allows two of the three to see over the barrier.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The middle frame labeled "<em>equity</em>", each person has a different setup:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>We still have three individuals of different heights.</li>
      <li>The tallest has no accommodation, the next shortest has one accommodation, and the shortest has two accommodations.</li>
      <li>The barrier still exists.</li>
      <li>This arrangement allows all three to see over the barrier.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The final frame labeled "<em>liberation</em>", all restrictions are removed:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>We still have three individuals of different heights.</li>
      <li>The barrier has been removed.</li>
      <li>No accommodations are being used.</li>
      <li>This arrangement allows all three to see the game.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>In this graphic, the left panel represents inaccessibility; the middle panel represents accommodation, and the right panel represents accessibility.</p>

  </contents>
</slide>

<slide>
  <title>Accommodation</title>
  <contents>

    <p style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; border: 3px solid #eee"><img src="images/equity.png"  alt="Children of different heights watching a baseball game from the outfield illustrating the concept of equity" title="detailed description follows"/></p>

<p>Accommodation means that some aspect of a system - for example a document or facility - has been adapted or modified to meet the needs of a specific individual or group.</p>

<p>Accommodations are patches or "temporary fixes", applied retroactively to overcome barriers in the environment or system.</p>

<p>Referring back to the graphic, by using what is available - the boxes - and reorganizing these, the system can be changed so all can view the game. An accommodation has been made - the system (the boxes) has been changed. The barrier still exists, therefore, if the accommodation is removed, there is once again the potential for inaccessibility.</p>

<p>In a classroom setting, an example of an accommodation may include an alternate version of a print document for a student who is visually impaired, such as an electronic text copy or audio file. An another example may include extra time or non-distractive environments for text taking for a student with a cognitive disability.</p>

  </contents>
</slide>

<slide>
  <title>Accessibility</title>
  <contents>

    <p style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; border: 3px solid #eee"><img src="images/liberation.png"  alt="Children of different heights watching a baseball game from the outfield illustrating the concept of liberation" title="detailed description follows"/></p>

    <dl>
      <dt>Accessibility:</dt>

      <dd>Different from Accommodation.</dd>

      <dd>Signifies the degree to which products and systems (the environment) can be used effectively by people with disabilities.</dd>

      <dd>Designs and practices that ensure both "direct access" (i.e. unassisted) and "indirect access" meaning compatibility with a person's assistive technology (for example, computer screen readers).</dd>

      <dd>Accessible Technology (AT) is technology that is designed for use by the greatest number of people, including people with disabilities, and doesn't require adaptation or modification to remove barriers to access or operation.</dd>

      <dd>Conversely, the technology that presents barriers to users with disabilities is "inaccessible".</dd>

    </dl>

    <p>Consider the graphic now. It is the barrier (the fence) that has been removed. By this change, the environment is changed and regardless of height, all three people can see the game. Viewing of the game is permissible from this spot by anyone, including those with disabilities. This is a result of accessibility, it benefits everyone.</p>

    <p>In order to benefit everyone, accessibility in technology must be achieved through designing, developing, purchasing, implementing, and supporting systems that provide an equivalent user experience to all users, regardless of disability or the way they access the technology. It must be a part of the complete process from beginning to end.</p>

    <p>While it is important to understand that there will always be a need for accommodation and remediation in inaccessible systems (in both the physical and electronic world), concepts of accessibility and inclusive design reflect the social model of disability, in which systemic barriers are minimized for the good of all.</p>
  </contents>
</slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Disability Barrier: Color Contrast</title>
    <contents>

<p>Rachel R. Vasquez posted on the A11y Project website about Color Contrast:</p>

<blockquote>"On the web, color contrast is about finding colors that not only provide maximum contrast, but provide enough contrast between content and the background for anyone with low vision impairments and color deficiencies. This doesn’t mean you have to limit your colors to complementary colors as we just talked about - but the contrast should be kept in mind all the same. The text and non-decorative images need to be clearly legible for everyone regardless of whether they have moderately low vision or color deficiencies. We can check colors for contrast by using one of many contrast tools online."</blockquote>


<p>A contrast ratio of 3:1 is the minimum standard for text and vision. For those with visual impairments however, the contrast ratio standard is 4.5:1. Yet, what does this mean? If colors, and the shades of each color are assigned numbers, then you start putting those next to each other, then you start getting these ratios. The idea is that you have to have enough contrast variation between a background and foreground color so that readability is made simple.</p>

<p>The following chart shows examples of good contrasting colors. Where no text is in a space indicates a contrast ratio below the minimum standard of 3:1.</p>

<p style="text-align: center"><img src="images/colorcontrast.png" alt="Color contrast chart" style="width: 90%; border-bottom: 1px solid black"/></p>

    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Disability Barrier: Structure</title>
    <contents>
      <dl>
        <dt>Landmarks</dt>
        <dd>Identifies major sections of content on the page.</dd>
        <dd>Visual layout and alignment is often used to visually identify sections of content.</dd>
        <dd>Screen readers can navigate the landmark structure of the page.</dd>
        <dt>Headings</dt>
        <dd>Identifies the structure of content within a section of content or a document.</dd>
        <dd>Often used to label landmarks on the page.</dd>
        <dd>Screen readers can navigate the landmark structure of the page.</dd>
        <dt>Page Title</dt>
        <dd>Identifies the individual page within a website/application.</dd>
        <dd>Identifies the website/application be used.</dd>
        <dd>Read by screen readers when the page is first loaded.</dd>
      </dl>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Disability Barrier: Links and Forms</title>
    <contents>
      <dl>
        <dt>Role</dt>
        <dd>Identifies the type of content or control (e.g. heading, list item, checkbox..)</dd>
        <dt>Accessible Name</dt>
        <dd>Provides a label for a form control or link.</dd>
        <dt>Accessible Description</dt>
        <dd>Additional information about images, form controls and wdigets</dd>
      </dl>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Disability Barrier: Keyboard and Focus Styling</title>
    <contents>
      <dl>
        <dt>Tab Navigation</dt>
        <dd>Using the <kbd>tab</kbd> to navigate interactive content on the page.</dd>
        <dt>Keyboard Support in Widgets</dt>
        <dd>Typically </dd>
        <dt>Skipping to main content</dt>
        <dd></dd>
        <dt>Focus Styling</dt>
        <dd></dd>
      </dl>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title></title>
    <contents>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Accessibility Laws</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Rehabition Act of 1973</li>
        <li>American with Disabilities Act (ADA)</li>
        <li>Section 508: Information Technology Accessibility</li>
        <li>Office of Civil Rights (OCR) complaints</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Rehabition Act of 1973</title>
    <contents>
     <div class="quote">
       No otherwise qualified individual with a disability in the United States... shall, solely by reason of her or his disability, be excluded from participation in, be denied the benefits of, or be subjected to discrimination under any program or activity receiving Federal financial assistance.
     </div>
     <ul>
       <li><a href="http://www2.ed.gov/policy/speced/reg/narrative.html">Rehabition Act of 1973</a></li>
       <li>Civil right (cannot discriminate)</li>
       <li>Organizations receiving federal money (e.g. states, universities..)</li>
       <li>Accessible programs and services</li>
       <li>Preferred accessible format</li>
       <li>At the same time</li>
       <li>Established the <a href="http://www.access-board.gov/">Access Board</a> to develop standards for implementation</li>
     </ul>

    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>American with Disabilities Act (1992)</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Extended coverage to public accomodations (e.g. businesses, non-profits, private education)</li>
        <li>Published standards for:
          <ul>
            <li>Buildings</li>
            <li>Transportation sytems</li>
            <li>Telecommunications</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>No standards for computing and network technologies</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Section 508 Standards for Electronic and Information Technology (2000)</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://www.access-board.gov/guidelines-and-standards/communications-and-it/about-the-section-508-standards/section-508-standards">Section 508 Standards for Electronic and Information Technology (2000)</a></li>
        <li>Only for Federal agencies and states receiving Tech Act grants</li>
        <li>Based on W3c Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 1.0 Level A requirements</li>
        <li>Established US federal accessibility standard for the Internet</li>
        <li>Compliance could be monitored and enforced</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title>Revised Information and Communication Technology (ICT) Standards and Guidelines (2017)</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.access-board.gov/guidelines-and-standards/communications-and-it/about-the-ict-refresh">Information and Communication Technology (ICT) Standards and Guidelines (2017)</a></li>
        <li>W3C <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.0</a> Level A and AA requirements</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>International Web Accessibility Laws</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://webaim.org/articles/laws/world/">WebAIM: World Laws</a></li>
        <li>Canada</li>
        <li>Europe</li>
        <li>United Kingdom</li>
        <li>Asia</li>
        <li>All have adopted some form of W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.0</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Office of Civil Right (OCR) Complaints in Higher Education</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://www.d.umn.edu/~lcarlson/atteam/lawsuits.html">Higher Education Accessibility Lawsuits Complaints, and Settlements</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://ati.calstate.edu/index.php?page=61">California State University System (2009)</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.readingrights.org/464">Electronic E-Books: Kindle pilot project (2009)</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://accessibility.psu.edu/nfbpsusettlement/">Penn State University (2010)</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.justice.gov/crt/about/edu/documents/montanaagree.pdf">University of Montana (2012)</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/us-education-department-reaches-agreement-youngstown-state-university-ensure-equal-access-its-websites-individuals-disabilities">Youngstown State (2014)</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/13/education/harvard-and-mit-sued-over-failing-to-caption-online-courses.html?_r=0">Harvard/MIT captioning of MOOC videos (2015)</a></li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Establish a standard</li>
        <li>Publicize the standard</li>
        <li>Implementation plan</li>
        <li>Accessibility must be managed</li>
        <li>Procurement</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
  </slide>

</slides>


